Guide to the John Gould Fletcher Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Gould Fletcher Collection
1911-1965
YCAL MSS 467
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(9 boxes)
The John Gould Fletcher collection contains material by, about, and relating to American poet John Gould Fletcher.
Fletcher, John Gould, 1886-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired through various gifts and purchases, 1942-1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
John Gould Fletcher (1886-1950)
John Gould Fletcher, born in Little Rock, Arkansas and educated at Phillips Academy and Harvard (1903-1907), was a Pulitzer Prize-winning poet and author. Fletcher lived in England for years before returning home to Arkansas where, in the 1920s and 1930s, he was active with a group of writers and poets known as the Southern Agrarians. Works by Fletcher include Fire and Wine (1913), Goblins and Pagodas (1916), The Black Rock (1928), the autobiography Life is My Song (1937), Selected Poems (1938), for which he was awarded the Pulitzer Prize, The Burning Mountain (1946), and the history Arkansas (1947). Fletcher married twice, in 1916 to Florence Emily "Daisy" Arbuthnot, and in 1936 to childrens' book author Charlie May Simon.
Scope and Contents
The John Gould Fletcher collection contains writings, journals, correspondence, and photographic and other materials by, about, or relating to the poet John Gould Fletcher. The collection features original drafts, many corrected, for individual poems and collections of poems, including Breakers and Granite (1921) and "Rest in the Harbour" (1916-1917), and short essays. In addition to drafts of original writings by Fletcher, the collection contains reproductions of journals and correspondence, and other papers such as documents, clippings, and printed ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Writings, 1913-1947. II. Journals, undated. III. Correspondence, 1911-1965. IV. Photographic Material, 1951-1960. V. Other Material, 1922-1956.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Microfilms; Poets; Authors; Fletcher, John Gould, 1886-1950
- Writings, 1913-1947; Series I; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings contains original drafts, many corrected, for early writings by John Gould Fletcher. Writings consist chiefly of drafts for individual poems and collections of poems, such as Breakers and Granite (1921), "Rest in the Harbour" (1916-1917), and "The Rock in the Storm," but drafts for a number of short essays can also be found.
  Unsorted writings are filed at the end of the alphabetical run of titles.
  - "1939: A Poem", [circa 1940] (Box 1)
  - "Antistrophe", [19]13 September (Box 1)
  - "Blake", undated (Box 1)
  - Breakers and Granite, 1916-1920; 2 (Box 1)
  - "A Carol for the Coincidence of Christmas and Judgement Day", 1931 December (Box 1)
  - "Carter's Folly", undated (Box 1)
  - "Christmas at Sixty", 1947, undated (Box 1)
  - The Dance Over Fire and Water by Elie Faure, undated (Box 1)
  - "Death's March", 1915, undated (Box 1)
  - "Fruit of Flame", 1914 (Box 1)
  - "H. D.", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Hand in the Dark", 1927 June 18 (Box 1)
  - "Japanese Prints", 1914 May (Box 1)
  - "Literature and the Professors", undated (Box 1)
  - "London at War", 1918 December (Box 2)
  - "Love", 1913 (Box 2)
  - "Love Song", 1913 September (Box 2)
  - "Magazitis Americana: A Diagnosis", undated (Box 2)
  - "Midwinter Love", 1916 February (Box 2)
  - [Notebooks], 1917-1925; 2 (Box 2)
  - "Old South Revisited", undated (Box 2)
  - "On Liberty and Canal Boats", undated (Box 2)
  - Parables, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - [Poems], undated (Box 2)
  - "Rest in the Harbour", 1916-1917 (Box 2)
  - "The Rock in the Storm", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Street Musician", 1913 (Box 3)
  - "Strophe", undated (Box 3)
  - "Ten Years", 1924-1925 (Box 3)
  - "Three Epitaphs on John Gould Fletcher", 1913 October 17 (Box 3)
  - "To Columbus", 1924, undated (Box 3)
  - The Tree of Life, 1914-1915 (Box 3)
  - Unsorted, undated; 2 (Box 3)
- Journals, undated; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series II. Journals appears to contain typescript transcriptions from notebooks for the dates 1904 through 1949.
  - Journals (1904-1936), undated; 23 (Box 4)
  - Journals (1938-1949), undated; 13 (Box 5)
  - Unsorted, undated; 12 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, 1911-1965; Series III; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Series III. Correspondence consists chiefly of copies or transcriptions of letters to and from Fletcher and original third-party correspondence, though original letters from Fletcher can also be found.
  Dates assigned below represent circa dates for the dates of the original correspondence rather than the copies or transcriptions.
  Unsorted correspondence can be found at the end of the alphabetical run of correspondents.
  - Aiken, Conrad, 1919-1948, undated; 3 (Box 6)
  - Anderson, Lee, undated (Box 6)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1920-1945, undated (Box 6)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1920-1937; 2 (Box 6)
  - Cournos, John, 1920-1935, undated; 3 (Box 6)
  - Greer, Scott, 1943-1949, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1917, undated (Box 7)
  - Knollenberg, ----, 1942 March (Box 7)
  - Monro, Harold, 1911-1935; 3 (Box 7)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1927-1946 (Box 7)
  - Nash, Paul, undated (Box 7)
  - O'Conor, Norreys Jephson, 1937-1952 (Box 7)
  - Rogers, Lyman, 1905-1907 (Box 7)
  - Tate, Allen, 1927-1945, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Wilkinson, Marguerite, 1919, undated (Box 7)
  - [Business correspondence], 1950-1965; 2 (Box 7)
    Contains third-party correspondence
  - Unsorted, 1920-1960, undated; 3 (Box 7)
    Includes third-party correspondence
- Photographic Material, 1951-1960; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series IV. Photographic Material contains microfilm and slide transparencies of material relating to John Gould Fletcher which appears to have been assembled by Yale professor Norman Holmes Pearson for purposes of research on Fletcher and/or curation of the library's Fletcher collection. Microfilm documents correspondence between Fletcher and others and slide transparencies document locations in Arkansas.
  - Microfilm, 1951-1960, undated; 3 (Box 8)
  - Slide transparencies, undated (Box 8)
- Other Material, 1922-1956; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series V. Other Material consists of material by, about, or relating to John Gould Fletcher which appears to have been assembled by Yale professor Norman Holmes Pearson for purposes of research on Fletcher and/or curation of the library's Fletcher collection. Materials include original documents, copies of writings, correspondence, clippings, and printed ephemera.
  - Articles on Fletcher, 1953-1956, undated (Box 9)
  - "Bibliographical", 1935-[1937], undated (Box 9)
  - "Biographical", 1929-1956, undated (Box 9)
  - "Fletcher essay", 1946-1951, undated (Box 9)
  - Journal excerpts (1907), undated (Box 9)
  - "Miscellaneous material", 1922-1955, undated (Box 9)
  - "Miscellaneous notes by Fletcher", 1948 August 11 (Box 9)
  - "Mrs. Fletcher's Journal on Dr. Schweitzer", undated (Box 9)
  - "Permissions", undated (Box 9)
  - Yale exhibition, 1942, undated (Box 9)